Bruce Springsteen - 2016 - Seattle - Adam Raised a Cain - HQ Audio edited by littleflutea
music ...
1,2,3,4
In the summer that I was baptized
My father held me to his side
As they put me into the water
He said how on that day I cried
We were prisoners of love,
a love in chains
He was standin' in the door,
I was standin' in the rain
With the same hot blood burning in our veins
Adam raised a Cain (yeah)
All of the old faces
Asked you why you're back
They fit you with position
And the keys to your daddy's Cadillac
In the darkness of your roomYour mother calls you by your true name
You remember the faces, the places, the names
You know it's never over,
it's relentless as the rain
Adam raised a Cain (yeah)
solo ...
solo...
Yeah ...
In the Bible Cain slew Abel
And East of Eden mama he was cast
You're born into this life paying
For the sins of somebody else's past
Well Daddy worked his whole life
for nothing but the pain
Now he walks these empty rooms
looking for something to blame
You inherit the sins, you inherit the flames
Adam raised a Cain (yeah)
Lost but not forgotten,
from the dark heart of a dream
Adam raised a Cain (yeah)
Oh oh, oh oh oh oh
solo...
lyrics edited by littleflute (2021.5.8)