- Welcome to the Cybertruck unveil.
(crowd cheering)We've created an exoskeleton.
(bangs) (laughs) (cheering)
Nice.Now, hit the Cybertruck.
(bangs)(crowd cheering)
Yeah, what else can we dowith this truck, let's shoot it?
That's a nine millimeter bullet shot at the door.
So, it's ultra hard, cold rolled,stainless steel alloy that we've developed.We're gonna be using the same alloyin the star ship rocket and in the Cybertruck.
Let's show the glass demo.
So, first this is regular glass,this is like normal glass, car glass.
We're going to show you what happenswith normal car glass.
(thuds)Now, I'll show you Tesla Armor Glass.(crowd cheers)Yeah.
(thuds)(mumbles)
Alright France, could you try to break this glass, please?
(crowd cheers for France)
Yeah.
- You sure?
- [Elon] Yeah.
(glass shatters)
Oh, my ...Well,
maybe that was a little too hard.- Yeah.(laughing)
- Man, should we try the rear?- Let's try. - Yeah.(crowd commenting)
- It didn't go through. - That's true.- So, that's a plus side.- Let's try the rear.- Try that one, really, okay, sure.
(glass shatters) (laughter)- Aww man!- It didn't go through.(laughing)
All right.(crowd commenting)Ah, not bad.
(laughing)A little room for improvement.(laughing)Anyway, in addition the car has an adaptive air suspension.
The rear is a 100 cubic feet, six and a half foot length,bed length, up to 3500 pounds of pay load.
(cheering)
So, let's see on-road performance.
(crowd commenting and exclaiming)
In terms of off-road performance,it's gonna have the best angular, approach angle,
best clearance heights, best departure angle.
People are really going off roadthis is going to be great, you could basicallydo the Baja Rally in this thing.
We have three ranges.(clapping and cheering)
So, obviously they'll have access to all the super chargers.
Be capable of more than 250 kilowatts,we'll reveal the actual number later.
And, it has onboard outlets for 110 and 220 volts.
And, as a little plus, because it's got an air suspension,
we can tap off the air suspensionso you have a pneumatic source,
so you have a, yeah.
(crowd cheering and clapping)
Onboard air compressor.Of course, it'll come with autopilot standard.
(crowd cheering)Yeah.
And that's gonna--(crowd roars, whistles)
That's the price without any incentives.That's just like the price without any incentives.
Yup, so you can order now if you would like?
(crowd cheers)Alright, thank you!Oh wait!
We have,(crowd shouting)we also made an ATV, so.
(crowd cheering)
(dramatic music)(crowd cheers and comments)(cheering)
So, after the air suspension, you can drop real low
and you go high on the other side, which pull as load bolt.
So, you got it load bolt, you've got a built-in ramp,
so, you can take an ATV or dirt bike, whatever you want
and load it on the back.
(slides)(clicks)
Yes.Oh,(crowd cheering)
and it's currently plugged in and charging.
Alright. Thank you.(crowd cheers)
Oh, I should say also, we're goingto be offering rides in this whole night.
(crowd cheering and whistling)
Yeah, don't mind the glass.(crowd laughs)
(subtitle: littleflute)